Carey Orr Cartoons
Carey Orr Cartoons
1916-1962
Orr, 1890-
54 linear ft.
Over 5,000 original editorial cartoons, color proofs and scrapbooks of published cartoons
149439
Biographical History
Carey Orr (1890-1967) was a Pulitzer prize winning American editorial cartoonist.
Born in Ada, Ohio on January 17 1890, Carey Cassius Orr later moved to Spokane, Washington to live with his father. As a teenager, he took a correspondence course in cartooning. But following high school, Orr studied math and engineering at his father’s urging. Orr went on to find success as a semi-professional baseball pitcher and used his earnings to study at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts.
Orr worked briefly for the Chicago Examiner and also as editorial cartoonist for the Nashville Tennessean from 1912 to 1917. While in Nashville, Orr was frequently the target of editorials by the opposition paper, the Banner ran by Major E.B. Stahlman. Orr's work also appeared in Literary Digest and Cartoons Magazine. In 1917, Orr returned to Chicago as an editorial cartoonist for the Chicago Tribune, filling in for John T. McCutcheon. Orr created the "Tiny Tribune" strip that appeared in the paper; each of the four panels caricatured a section of the paper. Eventually, Orr replaced John T. McCutcheon.
Orr received the Pulitzer Prize for editorial cartooning in 1961 for his October 8, 1960 cartoon. He also won several awards from the Freedoms Foundation and was presented with a gold medal from the United States government for his World War I cartoons. He was also featured on the television program, This is Your Life. Orr also is credited with drawing the "The Kernel Cootie" strip from approximately 1919 to 1922.
Orr retired from the Chicago Tribune on January 1, 1963. He died on May 16, 1967 at Evanston Hospital.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Carey Orr Cartoons are arranged in two series and contain original editorial cartoons, colored proofs of original cartoons and scrapbooks of published cartoons.
Cartoons (1917-1962) consists of approximately 5,314 original editorial cartoons drawn by Orr, primarily for the Chicago Tribune. Orr's work focused on local, state, national and international politics. His cartoons often feature lots of text used to label particular elements as well as signage and dialogue. From 1943 onward, for many dates, there are also photostat proofs or copies of the same cartoon that have been colored.
Early works are dated with only years. Other cartoons often contain more than one date, in the form of stamps with engraver's dates and other dates possibly indicating intended publication. For the purposes of this inventory, xxx dates have been used. Original works measure 14 ½" x 17 ½" and were drawn in ink on illustration board. Photostats measure approximately 9" x 10".
Please note, part of the inventory below is a detailed item-level description of cartoons from 1916-1928. Items from these years have been assigned numbers. The remaining years have been described at the box level with dates only.
The Scrapbooks (1943-1962) series contains 17 scrapbooks of Orr's color editorial cartoons. The originals have been disassembled and foldered; one has been retained in its original form. Accompanying some scrapbooks are lists of dates with some title information and information about cartoons not represented in the scrapbooks.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Orr, 1890-; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress. -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Industrial relations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Illinois -- Chicago.; New Deal, 1933-1939 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Illinois -- Chicago.; Cartoonists -- Tennessee -- Nashville.; Editorial cartoons -- Illinois -- Chicago.; Editorial cartoons -- Tennessee -- Nashville.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Chicago tribune.; United States -- Politics and government-- 20th century -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Scrapbooks.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carey Orr, 1963.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - 1916-1928
    - Beginning to blame their masters?, 1916; 1916.0001.Orr; Central Powers" and "Allies" represented by pit bull dogs. A "Crowned Head" behind each dog twisting their tails with captions "Sic-'em!" Verso has preliminary sketches with captions "Dogs of war and the wolf at the Door" and "Food distributer." (Oversize 1)
    - Fog!, 1916; 1916.0002.Orr; Ship of State" with "Wilson" at the helm headed in the direction of "The Uncertain Future." Uncle Sam on board holding a small lifesaver with title "Unadequate Defense." Verso has preliminary sketches for unknown drawing. "6 Ply, Wedding Bristol, Plate finish." (Oversize 1)
    - Remove this blot!, 1916; 1916.0003.Orr; Uncle Sam showing a US Flag with stain on it titled "Child Labor" to "Congress" represented by a woman at a wash board and "Legislation" represented by a wash tub. The U.S. Capitol in background with a laundry line and laundry attached. (Oversize 1)
    - Stepping stones., 1916; 1916.0004.Orr; "Prussian Autocracy" represented by military boots walking over mounds of dead bodies covering the ground titled "German People." Verso filled with preliminary sketches of machinery, and pulleys. (Oversize 1)
    - A bad time to drop the oars., 1917; 1917.0001.Orr; A rowboat with oar titled "Ship Construction" has a man sitting at one end with arms crossed and titled "Striker" opposite Lady Liberty titled "Columbia." She has dropped her oars and is looking over her shoulder as they head over a waterfall titled "Submarine Toll" and the word "Defeat" rising in the mist. (Oversize 1)
    - Falling short., 1917; 1917.0002.Orr; Uncle Sam dressed in fisherman's rain gear stands on a dock with a tiny cannon titled "U.S. Ship Construction" that has fired an anchor attached to a long rope plunging into the water. In the background is a sinking boat titled "U-Boat Sinking." (Oversize 1)
    - Gas., 1917; 1917.0003.Orr; Uncle Sam is standing in trenches ready to don a gas mask titled "The Will to Win." Next to him is his rifle with the bayonet titled "Preparedness." The background is filled with gas clouds titled "German Propaganda." The clouds are filled with the text: "Germany is Invincible," "France is through," "England will Starve," "End this horrible slaughter," "This isn't America's War," "Italy is through," "Let's Quit," "Peace Talk," and "The war will soon be over." (Oversize 1)
    - The Giant Awakens, 1917; 1917.0004.Orr; Large bearded man titled "Russia" in tattered clothing looks upward with arms stretched out and hands upward. Chains attached to both wrists have been broken free. Bottom left corner has the inscription: Russian Revolution (Kerensky) Feb.1917. (Oversize 1)
    - Hurry up, America!, 1917; 1917.0005.Orr; A man titled "France" and a man titled "England" are blocking a large wooden door titled "West Front." A saber titled "The Hun" that has penetrated the door." A paper overlay was used during the creation of the image. A door mat with the title "U.S. Delay" was removed from the final image. The verso is filled with sketches of circles, triangles and machine gears." (Oversize 1)
    - The main artery., 1917; 1917.0006.Orr; Beavers wearing German military hats are gnawing down a tree titled "Ships." A sign in the background is labeled "U-Boat Menace." The branches of the tree are labeled "England," "Italy," "Our Army," and "France." The roots of the tree are labeled "Munitions," "Money," "Food," and "Men." (Oversize 1)
    - Still undecided., 1917; 1917.0007.Orr; A man labeled "Wilson" is standing in the rain scratching his head looking at a shop window displaying an umbrelled titled "Universal Military Service." In the rain and clouds the background forms the words "War with Germany." On the ground are the pattern of footsteps going in circles." Some lead white used to emphasize pouring rain. (Oversize 1)
    - A bad jolt, but looks what we got rid of.", 1918; 1918.0001.Orr; A vehicle labeled "Allies" hits a large rock in the road titled "Russian Catastrophe." As a result, a woman labeled "Peace Talk," is thrown out of the vehicle with a book titled "Peace without victory," and a paper scroll labeled "Pacifism," Surface abrasion where scratches were made to emphasize the movement of the vehicle in the drawing, and to whiten clouds of dust on the road." (Oversize 1)
    - But can he get away with it?, 1918; 1918.0002.Orr; A masked burglar labeled "Germany," carries an enormous trunk labeled "Russia" on his back. He looks out a small opening in a wall labeled "Allies' Peace Terms." (Oversize 1)
    - He vas cheating., 1918; 1918.0003.Orr; A German officer sits at a small table with cards coming out of his sleeves, jacket lapels and collar. He holds a revolver in his hand labeled "Peaceful Penetration," and looks down at a body lying on the ground labeled "Bolsheviki." The table is labeled "Peace Game," and the German soldier has his winnings piled next to him. (Oversize 1)
    - His final effort., 1918; 1918.0004.Orr; A German officer is lying down and extended over a globe labeled "The World." He holds a hammer in one hand labeled "German drive," and a nail in the other labeled "Spring 1918." He is frantically trying to hammer the nail into a board labeled "Property of Wilhelm, II," that he is trying to attach to the globe. Four other crooked nails labeled "1914," "1915," "1916," and "1917" are unsuccessfully holding the sign to the globe. (Oversize 1)
    - Kaiser: - You've got to do something this time or the game is over., 1918; 1918.0005.Orr; A large man wearing a baseball uniform and German military hat and labeled "Hindenburg" walks out of a dug-out with a large bat labeled "Spring Drive - 1918" over his shoulder. In the dug-out are two men in baseball uniforms. One has both hands grasped together in a motion to plead to the other man not to leave and the other man sits on the bench with his hand to his head looking distraught and wears a military hat with skull and crossbones. Lying on the ground are two bats labeled "Marne" and "Verdun." 7.3.5 is written in pencil on lower left recto. (Oversize 1)
    - The last round., 1918; 1918.0006.Orr; A fighter labeled "Allies" with the flags of those countries on the band of his trunks approaches a fighter labeled "Central Powers" who stands in his corner of the ring. Above this fighter is a bell labeled "Spring 1918" which is being pulled by "Father Time" outside of the ring. (Oversize 1)
    - Lost his appetite., 1918; 1918.0007.Orr; A large turkey with a body in the shape of a world globe and labeled "World Democracies" stands over a beat-up man in a tattered German military uniform labeled "Autocracy." A large axe labeled "Militarism" lies on the ground with a broken handle. Preliminary sketches for topic are on verso. (Oversize 1)
    - Next Washington's Birthday, 1918; 1918.0008.Orr; Uncle Sam as George Washington stands in a colonial costume leaning on a large axe with the blade labeled "U.S. Resources." "The World" dressed as another colonial figure Benjamin Franklin stands looking delighted at a tree labeled "Prussian Autocracy" which has been chopped down. Uncle Sam says, "Father, I cannot tell a Lie - etc." A preliminary sketch for an unknown drawing fills the verso. Men seated around a round table playing poker. "Novice of the game." is marked out. (Oversize 1)
    - Running short of building material., 1918; 1918.0009.Orr; A man in a Germany military uniform carrying a container with skulls and bones labeled "Last Reserves" ascends a mountain of skulls and bones labeled "German's Tower of Babel." At the top of the mountain is another German officer with his hands outstretched to the sky labeled "World Rule." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawing on verso. (Oversize 1)
    - Seasick., 1918; 1918.0010.Orr; Two men are on the top-side of a boat during a rough storm at sea. One man dressed as a chef is labeled "Wilhelm." He presents a dinner labeled "Success in Russia" to the seated, seasick man labeled "German People." In the distance the waves are labeled "War," "Allies," and "U. S. Determination." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawing fills verso. Images include those of a bear and a goal post labeled "Victory." (Oversize 1)
    - What will bring him to his knees., 1918; 1918.0011.Orr; A large man labeled "The German" stands proud before a man on his knees with his hands clasped and head lowered as if praying labeled the "Austrian People." He kneels on a rug labeled "Repentance for War." Above the large upright man is a large sack of money falling from the sky labeled "Billions Indemnity." (Oversize 1)
    - Vot's der use?, 1918; 1918.0012.Orr; A German soldier labeled "German People" holds a large axe in his one hand and wipes the sweat from his brow with a handkerchief in his other hand. He has chopped down several trees labeled "Romania," "Montenegro," "Serbia," and "Belgium." Two trees, "Italy" and "Russia" have axe marks in them, but are still standing. The soldier looks over his shoulder where trees labeled "England," "France," and "U.S." tower over him. A squirrel labeled "Victory" jumps from the tree labeled "Russia" to the tree labeled "France." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawings. Keywords: "The Armistice," "League of Nations," "Peace," "Business," "Towser." (Oversize 1)
    - Across., 1919; 1919.0001.Orr; A woman labeled "Eliza Prohibition" holds a baby labeled "Constitutional Amendment" in her arms as she jumps over icebergs in the shapes of states with their names Nebraska, Utah, New Hampshire, Oregon, Colorado, Iowa, Arkansas, California, Illinois, Indiana, N.C., Kan, etc.. On the distant shore are three howling dogs labeled "Brewer," "Distiller," and "Wine Merchant." The woman jumps to the shore that has the sign "Ratification." (Oversize 1)
    - Another fellow who thinks he's Sampson., 1919; 1919.0002.Orr; A bearded man labeled "Bolsheviki" stands between two columns trying to push them down. The columns are labeled "Civilization" and "World Democracy." A German soldier labeled "Autocracy" walks away and his word bubble reads "It can't be done!" (Oversize 1)
    - At its mercy., 1919; 1919.0003.Orr; A large bear with blood coming from his mouth stands on snow covered land labeled "Russia." A paper labeled "Bolshevik Army" is to the left of the bear. Approaching the bear and trudging through the snow is a man labeled "U.S. Force." He carries an American flag in one hand and a sword in the other. To his right is a sign that says "Archangel" Siberia." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawings on verso. Written on the verso: Peace,"Senate deadlock," "The Don-key," "W.J.B.," "Bryan Run," "Democratic opposition to .....," "Editorial," and "Can be ...to the donkey." (Oversize 1)
    - Awaiting the winner., 1919; 1919.0004.Orr; A large boxing ring is filled with boxers fighting. The ring is labeled "Fight for Control of German Gov't." Outside of the boxing ring is a military officer sitting down labeled "Allies." He sits behind a large bag labeled "War Indemnity," another labeled "Debt," and "German Debts." A large scroll is rolled up and labeled "War Bill." Verso is filled with doodles of circles, tubes, triangles and other shapes." (Oversize 1)
    - "Balking Again", 1919; 1919.0005.Orr; A man is riding a cart labeled "The People" pulled by a donkey labeled "Democratic Administration." The man reaches for a whip labeled "Public Opinion," as the donkey stops in front of a foot bridge labeled "Reconstruction legislation." The sign before the bridge reads "Preparedness for Peace." In the background was a bridge labeled "Preparedness for War 1914-1917" that the man and donkey has already passed over." "Balking Again" on recto upper left and on verso. (Oversize 1)
    - Can he put it across?, 1919; 1919.0006.Orr; A baseball player labeled "Senate" stands over homeplate that it is in the shape of the U.S. He holds a bat ready to hit. The pitcher is labeled "W.W." and the ball is actually a small globe labeled "World League." The catcher is in the foreground and his glove reads "Ratification." (Oversize 1)
    - Can't he see they are busy?, 1919; 1919.0007.Orr; "W.W." and "Foreign Diplomat" are sitting at a table labeled "European problems" playing checkers. A store clerk labeled "Congress" stands over them watching. A customer labeled "American Public" slams one fist on the counter and another hand in the air demanding service. An empty basket labeled "Needed Legislation" sits on the counter waiting to be filled. (Oversize 1)
    - C'mon home, 1919; 1919.0008.Orr; Uncle Sam stands in front of a saw and wood pile yelling "Oh Woodrow!" The stack of wood in the background reads "New problems "Preparedness Problem, "Our own business,"Rail Road Question," "Reconstruction problems," and "Problem." In the far distance is the top of the U.S. Capitol building. (Oversize 1)
    - The Cure., 1919; 1919.0009.Orr; A screaming, crying baby labeled "Europe's Bolshevism" lies in a cradle. The baby holds a broken rattle labeled "Law." On the floor is a pacifier and a medicine bottle labeled "Remedy," and a spoon. A hand offers a baby bottle labeled "Foodstuff." Verso is filled with doodles. (Oversize 1)
    - The danger of driving him too far., 1919; 1919.0010.Orr; A man labeled "Germany" is being forced to jump off a cliff by a bayonet. The bayonet has pierced a piece of paper labeled "French terms of Peace." At the bottom of a cliff are a mound of skulls and bones with a bear next to them. A sign next to the bear reads "Bolshevism - Russo-German Alliance." Verso contains preliminary sketches of a man preparing to jump from a cliff. (Oversize 1)
    - Elba or St. Helena, 1919; 1919.0011.Orr; The Kaiser stands on a rocky shore with water crashing on it's rocks. He leans forward on his sword looking downward. Across the water in the distance is smoke rising from a distant land labeled "Germany." Verso has some doodling and "High Prices" on one figure. (Oversize 1)
    - The end of the long journey., 1919; 1919.0012.Orr; Uncle Sam stands on a Railroad platform waiting for a train that is approaching from the distance. The rail road track is labeled "G. O. P." On his right is a donkey pulling a broken down cart labeled "Democratic Congress" that has lost it's back wheels along the rocky path to the platform. In the far distance is a sign that reads "Six years of it." (Oversize 1)
    - Fighting for the reins.", 1919; 1919.0013.Orr; A cart is filled with men fighting with large clubs and a gun. One man is being pushed off the cart. The reins of the cart is labeled "The Gov't" and is attached to the bones of a horse lying on the ground labeled "German Nation driving to death by W. Hohenzollern." Verso contains some unidentified preliminary sketches and "Fighting for the Reins." (Oversize 1)
    - Gagged, 1919; 1919.0014.Orr; A large globe with a face on a newspaper titled "American Press" reads a newspaper "Censored News" which is being tied around the circumference of the globe. It is being tied at the top of the globe by "Burleson." The rope has a tag labeled "Government seizure of marine cables." The newspaper reads "Versailles Peace Conference censored by George Creel,"Making the World Safe for Democrats by George Creel," and several other non-descript articles with by-lines reading "by Creel." Doodling on the verso filling the entire area (Oversize 1)
    - A good way to express our appreciation., 1919; 1919.0015.Orr; A large hat with stars going around the band (Uncle Sam's hat) is lying on a street filled with coins and currency. The brim of the hat is labeled "United War Work Fund." Mounds of currency surround the hat. In the background attached to a brick building is a sign that reads: Bulletin: Yanks Bring Victory, Free World From Kaiserism, Germany forced to accept Armistice Terms - Kaiser abdicates - U.S. Soldiers bring glory to Nation, Negotiations under ... Versailles Confer.... Victory Results to Yank ..... Pershing's Army ....." Verso has pencil sketches ink doodles. "Carry Orr - in Tribune" (Oversize 1)
    - He started something., 1919; 1919.0016.Orr; A large man labeled "Germany" yells "Sic 'em!" to a dachshund labeled "Bolshevism." The man is between two doorways both labeled "Russia." The dog's head is coming out the doorway on the right and biting the coat-tails of "Germany." The dogs tail and back legs are just entering the door on the left. Verso has unidentified doodles. (Oversize 1)
    - His Ally., 1919; 1919.0017.Orr; A man sits with legs crossed and holds a tattered flag on a pole. He has knives in his boots, belt and holds a bloody dagger in his other hand. A pistol is also in his belt. The throne he sits in is labeled "Bolshevist Rule." Two large bombs rest at his feet as well as human skulls covering the ground. There is a sign which reads "Central Europe." Behind the throne looms a large ominous hooded figure labeled "Hunger." Verso filled with preliminary sketches of elephants labeled "G.O.P." and donkeys for identified drawings. (Oversize 1)
    - In step - The result of martial music., 1919; 1919.0018.Orr; A well-dressed suited man labeled "Capital" walks on a road with a man in his work overalls labeled "Labor."Labor" holds a sledgehammer over his shoulder. Both men are smiling at each other with their arms entwined. Behind them following in their path is a man labeled "Mars" banging a drum labeled "War Necessity." The men are headed in the direction of the sign on the road that reads "Peace." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawings on verso. (Oversize 1)
    - The Nurse., 1919; 1919.0019.Orr; Five large barbarian men each carrying a mace over their shoulders and wearing only a fur draped around them are labeled "1918," "1917," "1916," "1915," and "1914." They are walking away from a man, with a world globe for his head, labeled "The World." "The World" is on the ground with tattered clothes, holes in his shoes, a black eye, a large bump on his head, and holding his hand to his head. "The World" is turned and smiling to a nurse labeled "1919" and holds a bottle of medicine in her hand and bandage labeled "Reconstruction." (Oversize 1)
    - Oiling the waters., 1919; 1919.0020.Orr; A sailor in a rowboat labeled "We Allies," stands at the edge with an oiling can labeled "Archangel Miliary Expedition" oiling the waters labeled "Russia." Large waves in the background are labeled "Chaos," "Bolshevism," and "Unrest." Preliminary sketches for unknown drawings on verso. The number 720 appears on the lower left recto. (Oversize 1)